ALEX DA SILVA

Service Designer | Customer Experience Designer

Mobile (61) 0432 244 117 | Sydney, NSW, 2232 Email: <u>s.alexsilva@gmail.com</u> | Linkedin: <u>linkedin.com/in/alexdasilva1/</u>

SUMMARY

I am a highly skilled Service Designer with nearly **10 years** of experience and over **12,000 hours** of project work. My focus is on guiding businesses of all sizes, from startups to enterprises, to create services that meet their customers' needs, achieve business goals, and deliver a positive and memorable experience from the first interaction to ongoing engagement with the brand and services. In addition to my expertise in design, I bring valuable experience as a UI/UI Designer, Project Manager, Management Consultant, and Head of Marketing, which allows me to tackle complex problems and find the best balance between what is desirable, feasible, and viable.

PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

- Collaborate with cross-functional teams, including product managers, developers, and business stakeholders, to understand user needs and business requirements.
- Conduct customer research to analyse and understand customer needs and behaviours, including conducting empathy interviews with over 1,500 people interviewed to date.
- Analyse customer data and feedback to identify areas for improvement.
- Develop user personas, customer journey maps, and service blueprints to create a holistic view of the ecosystem.
- Develop communication and marketing strategies for the service and collaborate with other departments to ensure consistency in messaging and customer experience.
- Design prototypes to test ideas and identify shortcomings.
- Design and test customer-facing interfaces, such as websites and digital products.
- Develop and implement training programs to improve customer service skills among employees.
- Monitor and evaluate customer experience metrics.
- Work independently and as part of a team, demonstrating problem-solving skills, effective time management, and the ability to meet deadlines.
- Facilitate workshops and design processes, measuring success in a way that matters to business stakeholders.
- Demonstrate a strong understanding of design methodology and experience working in an agile environment.
- Possess excellent facilitation skills to lead internal workshops and co-design sessions with clients.
- Communicate effectively and manage client relationships to generate high-level impact in their processes.

- Support project planning, management, and reporting of deliverables.
- Proficient with design and prototyping tools such as Figma.
- Develop templates and tools to support Service Design thinking.
- Train others on design principles and agile approaches, having trained over 2,000 people to date.
- Find the best balance between what is desirable, feasible, and viable to create successful business outcomes.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

SERVICE DESIGNER

Australia, 05/2023 - Present (Full-time)

Civic Disability Services is a service provider dedicated to supporting individuals with disabilities in realising their full potential.

- Guiding and supporting internal teams and projects, ranging from improving existing processes to creating new programs and services.
- Building and Implementing an end-to-end Civic design process to leverage the power of a Human-Centred Design (HCD) mindset for every project while connecting it with disability industry principles, theory of change, business strategy and values, Civic tools and processes, and so on.
- Contributing to the establishment of a new team called Impact & Strategy, with a focus on fostering a HCD mindset.
- Harnessing a data-driven mindset by leveraging internal data from Customer Relationship Management (CRM) systems, and conducting research through various methodologies such as desk research, quantitative and qualitative analysis, descriptive research, observation, and other proven techniques.
- Facilitating workshops based on Design Thinking, HCD, and co-design principles.
- Leading discovery processes to enhance the overall customer experience.
- Executing design processes and leveraging design methods and tools, such as service blueprinting, customer research, customer journey, personas, and so on.
- Designing prototypes to test ideas and identify areas for improvement.
- Mapping the current state of the business, services, and processes to identify opportunities for enhancement at both the business and customer levels.
- Leading a program called Big Idea focused on motivating employees to share ideas that might become a project or service, delivering improved customer experience.
- Leading the design phase for a customer portal, overseeing user research, feature definition, problem statement creation, ideation, wireframing, and low-fidelity prototyping.

SERVICE DESIGNER AND PROJECT MANAGER

Australia, 12/2021 - 03/2023 (Full-time)

Citadel.run - Software as a Service (SaaS) solution for managing Amazon Web Services (AWS) cloud infrastructure, focused on Financial Services and Healthcare industries.

Key Achievements:

- Implemented an end-to-end design process to guide the product development team, from the discovery and research processes to feature releases.
- Conducted workshops to disseminate and guide people about design and agile processes.
- Released over 15 features, following the established design process.
- Supported the creation of a 'partner model', which accelerated the sales cycle and reframed the business model.
- Created a marketing foundation and implemented a marketing strategy based on customer touch points.
- Developed a brand guide for the product user interface.

Responsibilities:

- Leading discovery processes based on a Human-Centred Designer mindset to support customer understanding, such as Design Thinking and Design Sprint.
- Facilitating workshops such as Lean Inception and Objectives and Key Results (OKRs) to prioritise features, build a product roadmap, and provide more alignment between areas.
- Implementing design processes and design systems such as customer research, user flow, user experience, and user interface.
- Designing prototypes to test ideas and identify shortcomings.
- Managing, Supporting and guiding the development team through agile and innovative methodologies such as Scrum.
- Supporting the planning, management, and reporting of projects and deliverables.
- Designing and conducting experiments to optimise and improve business results.
- Building and validating the Citadel value proposition and product market fit.
- Tracking current business situations to support Citadel's C-levels in understanding and improving the Citadel solution.
- · Budget management.

SERVICE DESIGNER AND MANAGEMENT CONSULTANT

Australia, 12/2020 - 12/2021 (Full-time) | Australia, 03/2020 - 12/2020 (Contractor)

DNX Solutions - Australian cloud consulting firm and AWS advanced partner focused on cloud transformation projects.

Key Achievements:

- Developed and implemented a customer-centric marketing foundation that focused on improving the customer experience at all touchpoints, resulting in increased customer satisfaction and loyalty.
- Established and streamlined processes across departments, including Marketing, Operations, and Sales, to identify and report customer needs and opportunities, resulting in improved business performance.

- Successfully communicated the importance of having a clear understanding of the market, customer personas, customer journey, value propositions, and other key factors to various stakeholders within the organisation, resulting in improved alignment and decision-making.
- Conducted design methodology and OKRs workshops, empowering employees to apply design processes and align their work with business goals, resulting in increased productivity and innovation.
- Launched 5 new solutions based on customer needs that were identified through the design process.

Responsibilities:

- Uncovering business needs and developing strategies for being more effective and efficient.
- Engaging with customers to understand their needs, identify opportunities, turn them into business requirements, and create new offerings to support growth.
- Designing and conducting experiments to optimise and improve business results.
- Leveraging agile and innovative approaches to manage and conduct projects.
- Taking responsibility for deploying changes and functional solutions to ensure better quality and NPS (Net Promoter Score).
- Tracking current businesses' situations to support high-level managers in understanding and providing improvements to DNX.
- Aligning projects with strategic business objectives to encourage discussions between leaders and their impact on different organisational levels.
- Running periodic workshops focused on business objectives, customer experience, and new technology in order to identify new opportunities or at least bring new insights and updates.
- Tracking different businesses, management models, and competitors to offer new ways to help and inspire the customer experience.
- Building reports, presentations, and documents to drive business decisions.

SERVICE DESIGNER AND CO-FOUNDER

Australia, 12/2018 - 02/2020

Design4Reap - Consulting business that uses Human-Centred Design as a business mindset. They are focused on assisting companies to transform and grow their businesses through design approaches.

Key Achievements:

 Accumulated about 1,000 project hours, and 500 interview hours while delivering projects for Australian and Brazilian companies - DNX Solutions, Sonepar Group, Smile Clothing, Lillah Kitchen, SoulViajero, and USTennis, among others.

Responsibilities:

- Delivering end-to-end design projects focused on identifying customer needs and providing solutions
 that fit clients' business models, from discovery to definition, to ideation, to prototype, to iteration, to
 implementation.
- Leveraging different design approaches, methodologies, and processes such as Design Thinking, Design Sprint, UX, UI, CX, and Lean Startup based on our customers' needs.

- Assisting businesses to design business models, digital products, features, services, branding, processes, strategies, and so on.
- Conducting quantitative and qualitative research from the end user to partners, to employees, providing a deep understanding of businesses and customers to be used as a data-driven.
- Analysing qualitative and quantitative data to identify opportunities or insights that empower our clients to make better decisions.
- Running remote and in-presence projects in Australia and Brazil, focused on identifying customer and market needs and providing solutions that fit clients' business models.
- Designing prototypes, from wireframes to high-fidelity, to test ideas and identify shortcomings.
- Conducting workshops and training focused on design and agile methodologies.
- · Managing and executing all those project phases.
- Building reports, presentations, and documents to drive business decisions.

SERVICE DESIGNER AND PROJECT MANAGER - Brazil, 03/2014 - 09/2018

Weme - A company that uses design methodologies to accelerate and transform business ecosystems. Weme's focus is helping to solve the biggest human challenges stimulating innovation and entrepreneurship across all stakeholders.

Key Achievements:

- Accumulated about 7,000 hours of projects, with more than 2,000 hours of users interviews, split
 into nearly 100 projects for companies such as Bosch, 3M, Unilever, Siemens, P&G, DHL,
 Karcher, Croda, ArcelorMittal, among others.
- More than 2,000 people were trained in the Design Thinking approach and more than 500 people in Agile Method.

Responsibilities:

- Transforming ideas and concepts into great business models. Running design sprints based on the Human-Centred Design approach.
- Applying diversified approaches to assist customer needs, such as Design Thinking, Business/Service Design, User Experience, Interaction Design, Agile Project Management, Traditional Project Management, Growth Hacking, Marketing, Strategic Plans, OKRs, Lean Startup, Business Model, and Golden Circle, among others.
- Working directly with users to identify their real needs and develop business requirements.
- Starting up new projects, managing the documentation, defining the best methods to use, agreeing
 with the team about the schedule and conducting weekly meetings with clients allowed us to identify
 opportunities and solve business problems.
- Mapping current businesses' situations through meetings with high-level managers allowing a
 complete understanding and applying necessary tools such as Business Model, Objectives Frame
 (Corporate, Branding, Project), Challenges to solve, Golden Circle (How, What, Why), principles,
 values, essence, and value proposition.
- Conducting and aligning projects with the client's strategic objectives and sharing amongst parties, encouraging discussions with business leaders about the impact that changes could have on different levels of the organisation OKR was used to evaluate project success.

- Deciding and studying different business and management models to offer new ways how to help and inspire changes in his client's businesses.
- Acting as a central reference, providing guidance and assistance in decision-making processes

EDUCATION

University of Sydney

Coding Boot Camp. Australia, 2024

TAFE NSW

UX/UI (Validating and updating skills). Australia, 2024

UNICAMP - University of Campinas

Graduate Diploma of Business Management and Strategy. Brazil, 2009 - 2011

ESAMC - Higher School of Administration

Bachelor of Marketing and Social Communication. Brazil, 2002 - 2007

LICENCES, CERTIFICATES, TRAINING

Data-Driven Design. Australia, 2023. Interaction Design Foundation

Design for the 21st Century with Don Norman. Australia, 2023. Interaction Design Foundation Methods to Design Better Products and Services. Australia, 2023. Interaction Design Foundation User Research: Methods and Best Practices. Australia, 2023. Interaction Design Foundation Member of Interaction Design Foundation. Australia, 2022. Interaction Design Foundation The ultimate HTML5 & CSS3 Series. Australia, 2021. Mosh

Lean Inception Facilitator. Australia, 2021. Caroli.org

Figma: Collaborative design from basic to responsive prototype. Australia, 2020. Udemy

UX: User Experience within the business. Australia, 2020. Udemy

AWS Business Professional. Australia, 2020. Amazon Web Services (AWS)

Prototyping. 2018. IDEO.org

Agile Scrum Master in Advanced Project Management. Brazil, 2018. Vega Consulting

Global Summit. United States, 2017. Singularity University

Agile Project Management Insights - Scrum. Brazil, 2016. Nakamura - Apud Et Al

Branding. Brazil, 2015. Insper

Design Thinking. Brazil, 2015. WEME School **Design and Future Thinking**. Brazil, 2015. ESPM

Mind Maps. Brazil, 2015. ESPM

Project Management - PMI. Brazil, 2014. ESPM

HARD SKILLS

Human-centred Design, Design Thinking, Design Sprint, User Experience, User Interface, User Research, Lean Startup, Lean Inception, Commercial Acumen, Agile, Project management (Scrum and PMI), OKRs, KPI, NPS, Business Model Canvas, Value Proposition, Golden Circle, Service Mapping and Blueprinting, Customer Journey, Stakeholder map, Ecosystem, Storytelling, Job Story,

Storyboard, POV, Golden Path, Persona, Canvas Innovation, Crazy 8's, Taxonomy, Sitemaps, Mood-board, A/B test, Prototyping, MVP, Roadmap, Strategy and Business, Marketing, Branding.

SOFT AND PEOPLE SKILLS

Problem-solving, Ability to work independently as well as in a multidisciplinary team, team leadership, multi-task confidently and productively, co-creative, optimist, empathetic, collaborative, good listener, strategic thinking, decision-making, excellent communication and presentation.

SOFTWARES AND TOOLS

Microsoft 365 (basic and advanced apps), Figma, FlowMap, Miro, ClickUp, Wrike, Asana, Trello, Webflow, WordPress, Avada, Fusion Blocks, Slack, HubSpot, Google products, Canva, and so on.

LANGUAGES

Portuguese - Native

English - Fluent